<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>[enzo]lutions</title>
        <link>http://enzolutions.com</link>
        <description>RSS feed for [enzo]lutions</description>
                <atom:link href="http://enzolutions.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
                    <item>
                <title>What is Cross-Origin Resource Sharing (CORS)</title>
                <description><![CDATA[<p>Nowdays is pretty common to transfer data between web applications via Web Services to  clients that require information on different interfaces such as REST, XMLRPC, JSON, JSON-RPC, SOAP and others.</p>

<p>Almost all sites today are built using JavaScript, generating AJAX calls with XMLHttpRequest mechanism to get information  from external sites. To enable this kind of comunication is necessary implement "cross-domain" requests would otherwise be forbidden by web browsers, per the <a target="_blank" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Same_origin_policy">same origin security policy</a>.</p>

<p>Lets imagine the following scenery: we have a frontend application using the domain http://a.com and this application wants to use data provided by a  backend site located in domain http://b.com. For security this type of communication is blocked and the end user will be only able to get the information from http://a.com, this scenario is exemplified in the following image.</p>

<p><img src="http://enzolutions.com/assets/img/crossdomain.png"/></p>

<p>To enable this kind of communication is requiered that your backed server (http//b.com) returns the specific HTTP Headers to enable CORS comunication. Below you can see an example of HTTP Header required.</p>

<pre><code>Access-Control-Allow-Credentials:true
Access-Control-Allow-Headers:X-CSRF-Token
Access-Control-Allow-Methods:POST,ADD,GET,PUT,DELETE,OPTIONS
Access-Control-Allow-Origin:http://localhost:8080
</code></pre>

<p>The header <em>Access-Control-Allow-Credentials</em> is only used if your request require some kind of authentication. You can read more information about all HTTP Headers at <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTTP/Access_control_CORS">Access Controls - CORS</a>.</p>
]]></description>
                <link>http://enzolutions.com/articles/2014/05/31/what-is-cross-origin-resource-sharing-cors/</link>
                <pubDate>Sat, 31 May 2014 09:45:57 -0600</pubDate>
                <guid>http://enzolutions.com/articles/2014/05/31/what-is-cross-origin-resource-sharing-cors/</guid>
            </item>
                    <item>
                <title>How to configure MySQL to import large database</title>
                <description><![CDATA[<p>On many occasions we need to install in our local enviroment a copy of production sites for development or debugging process, this entails that need to import large databases.</p>

<p>The most common error is that you cannot import the database because for some reason you loose the communication with the <a target="_blank" href="http://www.mysql.com/">MySQL</a> server, as shown below.</p>

<pre><code>$ /mysql -f -uroot -proot mydb -h 127.0.0.1 &lt; ~/Downloads/prod-mysql-2013-01-29.sql
ERROR 2006 (HY000) at line 6565: MySQL server has gone away
</code></pre>

<p>To fix this error you must to change the default configuration of MySQL.</p>

<p>MySQL store his configuration in a file commonly named my.cnf and could be located in different locations depending the OS version you have installed.</p>

<p>If you do not know the location of this file, you can use the following command shown below to determine where you expect to find locations MySQL settings.</p>

<pre><code>$ ./mysql --help | grep my.cnf
/etc/my.cnf /etc/mysql/my.cnf /Applications/MAMP/conf/my.cnf ~/.my.cnf
</code></pre>

<p>In my case I had MySQL as part of <a target="_blank" href="http://www.mamp.info/">MAMP</a> and this file is not created by default. For this reason I will create a new file located at <em>/Applications/MAMP/conf/my.cnf</em> becuase is one of the location where MySQL will look his configuration file.</p>

<p>I recommend to use the sample provided by MySQL documentation for large databases localed at <em>/usr/share/doc/mysql-server-5.0/examples/my-large.cnf.gz.</em></p>

<p>After copy the suggested configuration from documantion, I have to apply two changes to warranty the import process don't fail.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Remove Directive # <em>skip-locking</em></p></li>
<li><p>Increase setting <em>max_allowed_packet = 100M</em></p></li>
</ul>

<p>Then just be enough restart the MySQL server and try to import the database again.</p>

<p>You can check my version of my.cnf <a target="_blank" href="http://7sabores.com/sites/default/files/my.cnf_.txt">here</a></p>
]]></description>
                <link>http://enzolutions.com/articles/2014/05/28/how-to-configure-mysql-to-import-large-database/</link>
                <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2014 09:45:57 -0600</pubDate>
                <guid>http://enzolutions.com/articles/2014/05/28/how-to-configure-mysql-to-import-large-database/</guid>
            </item>
                    <item>
                <title>My blog is alive again!</title>
                <description><![CDATA[<p>Hello folks.</p>

<p>After many years without touch my personal website, I took the decision to put it back online.</p>

<p>Recently I have been writing technical documentation in Spanish in the website <a href="http://7sabores.com" target="_blank">7Sabores.com</a>. If you are wondering Why in Spanish? and if you read Spanish you can find my justification in the blog entry <a href='http://7sabores.com/blog/se-busca-en-espanol'>¿Se busca en Español?</a>.</p>

<p>I will not translate all my Spanish entries to English or viceversa, all depends my mood :P.</p>

<p>Also I have to say THANKS YOU to two great products <a targe="_blank" href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</a> and <a href="http://spress.yosymfony.com/">[S]press</a>. Without them this blog couldn't be possible.</p>

<p>See you around.</p>
]]></description>
                <link>http://enzolutions.com/articles/2014/05/21/my-blog-is-alive-again/</link>
                <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2014 09:45:57 -0600</pubDate>
                <guid>http://enzolutions.com/articles/2014/05/21/my-blog-is-alive-again/</guid>
            </item>
            </channel>
</rss>
